Department of Special Collections, Hesburgh Libraries of Notre Dame
American Colonial Currency Collection
- Pennsylvania Currency March 10, 1769Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaPennsylvaniaMarch 10, 1769, PA 03/10/69; David Hall and William Sellers;
  - Two Shillings17421 17421, 269; Signers: Stephen Collins, Luke Morris and James Penrose.; Size: 74 x 89mm (front border design: 71 x 87mm).
    Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" in a scroll at the bottom of the arms. The colony name has various spellings in this issue, on this denomination it appears as "Pensilvania." The back is blank.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EAHA mail bid auction of 03/28/98, lot 361, graded Very Fine.
  - Twenty Shillings831 831, 270; Signers: James Penrose, Stephen Collins and Luke Morris.; Size: 83 x 90mm (front border design: vertical dimension is 77 x 88mm; back border design: vertical dimension is trimmed off at bottom, horizontal dimension is 85mm).
    Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" in a scroll at the bottom of the arms. Above the arms the denomination is keyed to four crowns. The colony name has various spellings in this issue, on this denomination it appears in its current form "Pennsylvania ". The back has a nature print consisting of three fern branches with the roman numeral XX in white at the base of the bottom branch.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 1/13/96, lot 436.
- Pennsylvania Currency March 20, 1771Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaPennsylvaniaMarch 20, 1771, PA 03/20/71; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission of ฃ15,000 in bills of credit. The emission was authorized to be used for the defense of Philadelphia but was actually used for paving the streets. To be redeemed from the treasury for current bills of credit. Printed by David Hall and William Sellers in Philadelphia on paper containing mica flakes. Cast border cuts with the Penn family arms on the front and a nature print on the back. Printed in red and black with plates A and B. Throughout the denominations the spelling of the colony name "Pennsylvania" is found in various forms. This is the continuation of an anti-counterfeiting measure used by Franklin and Hall. Denominations issued were: 5s, 10s, 15s and 20s.
  - Twenty Shillings2068 2068, 271; Signers: Stephen Collins, Jacob Shoemaker, Joshua Howell (in red ink).; Size: 90 x 74mm (front border design: 88 x 77mm; back border design: 84 x 70mm).
    Printed in red and black ink. Numbering and first two signatures in black ink; third signature in red ink. No space had been planned for the numbering of the bills. On this example the numbering appears in the upper border design. The Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" are printed in red in the upper left. Above the arms the denomination is represented in red by four crowns. Colony name appears as "Pennsylvania ". The paper contains blue threads and mica flakes. On the back is a nature print containing three fern branches with XX and the letter S (for shillings) in white at the base of the bottom branch.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 12/2/95, lot 508.
- Pennsylvania Currency April 3, 1772Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaPennsylvaniaApril 3, 1772, PA 04/03/72; David Hall and William Sellers; James Smithers
  An emission of ฃ25,000 in bills of credit. Printed in Philadelphia by David Hall and William Sellers with engraved border cuts by James Smithers. The notes also contain the Penn family arms. The pence denominations are smaller with typeset backs and come in plates A-C. One shilling notes and above have nature prints on the back (a chevron design is on the 2s6d) with 1s-2s6d having plates A and B, while the 40s note comes in plates A-D and has a border cut signed "J. Smither Sculp." Pennsylvania was spelled in various ways on different denominations. Denominations issued were: 3d, 4d, 6d, 9d, 1s, 18d, 2s, 2s6d and 40s.
  - Two Shillings6459 6459, 272; Signers: Cadwalader Morris, Joseph Swift, Samuel Hudson.; Size: 80 x 88mm (front border design: 73 x 85mm; back border design: 64 x 82mm).
    On the front the right border cut (top lintel) is low and the left border cut (base) is high. Penn family arms with motto "Mercy Justice" appear on the front. Colony name appears as "Pensylvania". There is a nature print of a leaf on the back. The paper contains mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 541. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - One Shilling26391 26391, 526; Signers: Thomas Clifford, Thomas Coombe, Samuel Pleasants.
    Signed and numbered in brown ink.
    EANA mail bid auction 02/08/03 lot 645. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Two Shillings, Six Pence14654 14654, 527; Signers: Samuel Coates, James Wharton, and Joseph Dean.
    Signed and numbered in black ink. In the approximate center of the note is the denomination "Half-a-Crown." At the top and along the right side it is labeled "Two Shillings and Six-Pence.
- Pennsylvania Currency March 20, 1773Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaPennsylvaniaMarch 20, 1773, PA 03/20/73; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission of ฃ12,000 in bills of credit authorized for the construction of the Cape Henlopen Lighthouse and related buoys and piers. The back displays a cast cut of a lighthouse with the denomination of the bill incised in the plate in roman numerals, found in the lower left corner of the picture. There are four border cuts and the Penn shield on the front (on some of the 6s notes the shield was inadvertently printed upside down). Printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia on paper containing mica flakes. Each denomination has plates A and B. In each denomination the spelling of the colony name "Pennsylvania" is found in a different form. This is the continuation of an anti-counterfeiting measure used by Franklin and Hall. Usually numbered in red ink with at least one of the three signatures alos in red ink. Denominations issued were: 4s, 6s, 14s and 16s.
  - Four Shillings2272 2272, 273; Signers: Jacob Winey, middle red signature faded, Charles Jervis.; Size: 92 x 72mm (front border design: 86 x 70mm; back border design: 82 x 66mm).
    Numbering and first and third signatures in black ink, the second signature is faded and was in red ink. The top (or left) column on the front reads: "Light House" followed by "iv Shill." and the bottom (or right) column reads: "Piers and Buoys" followed by "iv Sh." The front also contains the Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice." Colony name appears as "Pensilvania ". The back of this denomination displays a cast cut of a lighthouse. The denomination of the bill is incised in a white arabic numeral "4" in the lower left corner of the cut; it is visible but quite faded in this example. The paper contains mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 4/26/97 lot 289. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Six Shillings, 274; Signers: John Steinmetz, Frederick Kuhl (faded in red), Benjamin Shoemaker.; Size: 88 x 74mm (front border design: 85 x 70mm; back border design: 82 x 66mm).
    The first and third signatures are in brown ink, the second signature and the numbering are in faded red ink. The top (or left) column on the front reads: "Piers and Buoys" followed by "vi Sh." and the bottom (or right) column (printed towards the center of the note) reads: "Light House" followed by "iv Shill." The front also contains the Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice." In this example, which is plate A, the arms were inadvertently printed upside down! In plate B the arms were oriented correctly. The colony name appears as "Pennsilvania ". The back of this denomination displays a cast cut of a lighthouse. The denomination of the bill is incised as a white arabic numeral "6" in the lower left corner of the cut. The paper contains mica flakes.
  - Fourteen Shillings716 716, 275; Signers: Frederick Kuhl, Jacob Winey (in red), Charles Jervis.; Size: 88 x 74mm (front border design: 85 x 70mm; back border design: 82 x 66mm).
    Plate number near bottom while in all others it is close to end of main text - Comments: The numbering and first signature are in a brown ink, the second signature is in red and the third signature is in a black ink. The left column on the front reads: "Piers and Buoys" followed by "XIV" at the column base and the right column reads: "Light House" followed by "XIV" In both cases the script faces outwards. The front also contains the Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice." The colony name appears correctly as "Pennsylvania ". The plate number is located near the bottom left corner on this denomination while in all other denominations of this emission it follows the final line of the main text. The back of this denomination displays a cast cut of a lighthouse. The denomination of the bill is incised in white roman numerals "XIV" in the lower left corner of the cut. The paper contains mica flakes.
  - Sixteen Shillings6317 6317, 276; Signers: John Steinmetz, Frederick Kuhl (in faded red ink), Benjamin Shoemaker.; Size: 89 x 70mm (front border design: 86 x 69mm; back border design: 82 x 66mm).
    The first signature is in a brown ink, the numbering and second signature are in a faded red ink, and the third signature is in black ink. The left column on the front reads downward: "Lighthouse" followed by a small "xvi" and the right column reads upward: "Piers & Buoys." followed by "16". In both cases the script faces outwards. The front also contains the Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice." The colony name appears correctly as "Pennsylvania ". The back displays a cast cut of a lighthouse with the denomination of the bill with the denomination of the bill incised in white roman numerals "XVI" in the lower left corner of the cut. The paper contains mica flakes.
- Pennsylvania Currency October 1, 1773Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaPennsylvaniaOctober 1, 1773, PA 10/01/73; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission of ฃ150,000 in bills of credit to revive the loan office system. Printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia in red and black ink with the Penn family arms on the front and a cast cut of a farm scene on the back. The farm scene differs slightly on each denomination. There are cast border cuts on the front with the border above the columns printed in both red and black ink. On the 10s-50s notes the text is partly in red so that it forms the roman numeral denomination of the note (X on 10s, XV on 15s, l for ฃ1 on 20s and L on the 50s note). The paper contains mica flakes. There are three signers with one frequently in red ink. Throughout the denominations the spelling of the colony name "Pennsylvania" is found in various forms. This is the continuation of an anti-counterfeiting measure used by Franklin and Hall. Denominations issued were: 18d, 2s, 2s6d, 5s, 10s, 15s, 20s and 50s.
  - Two Shillings1801 1801, 277; Signers: Benjamin Morgan, Barnaby Barnes, William Fisher, Jr.; Size: 70 x 90mm (front border design: 67 x 87mm; back border design: 62 x 83mm).
    The front right border is printed in red and black. Penn family arms with motto "Mercy Justice" appear in upper left corner. Colony name appears as "Pennsylvania". The paper contains mica flakes.
  - Ten Shillings27566 27566, 278; Signers: Thomas Leech, William Crispin, James Stephens.; Size: 94 x 68mm (front border design: 88.5 x 67mm; back border design: 84 x 62mm).
    Numbering and the first and third signatures in black ink with the second signature in red ink. The front is printed in red and black inks with the top border being in both colors and a red 'X' worked into the type of the main text. The Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" appears in the upper left. The denomination is represented with two crowns below the arms. Colony name appears as "Pensylvania ". The paper contains mica flakes.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EAHA mail bid auction of 5/23/98, lot 428 where it was graded as Crisp Gem Uncirculated.
  - Fifteen Shillings19924 19924, 279; Signers: James Harthy, Alexander Tod, Joseph Mifflin.; Size: 91 x 68mm (front border design: 88 x 67mm; back border design: 83 x 67mm).
    The front is printed in red and black ink with the top border being in both colors and a red 'XV' being worked into the set type (one line is shared by both letters). Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" appear in upper right. The denomination is keyed to three crowns below the text. Colony name appears as "Pensylvania". The paper contains mica flakes.
  - Fifty Shillings4070 4070, 280; Signers: Joseph Mifflin, Alexander Tod, James Hartley.; Size: 91 x 73.5mm (front border design: 88 x 67mm; back border design: 83 x 67mm).
    Signed and numbered in brown inks. The front is printed in red and black inks with the top border being in both colors and a red 'L' worked into the type of the main text. The Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" appears on the left center. The denomination is represented as ten crowns, five above and five below the arms. The colony name appears as "Pennsilvania ". The paper contains mica flakes with a piece of mica protruding on the inner side of the right column.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 1/13/96, lot 439.
- Pennsylvania Currency March 25, 1773Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaPennsylvaniaMarch 25, 1775, PA 03/25/73; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission of ฃ6,000 in bills of credit for the continued construction of the Cape Henlopen Lighthouse and buoys and piers. Similar to the first lighthouse issue of March 20, 1773. The back displays a cast cut of a lighthouse with the denomination of the bill incised in the plate in roman numerals, found in the lower left corner of the picture. Four border cuts and the Penn shield on the front. Printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia on paper containing mica flakes. Each denomination has plates A and B. In each denomination the spelling of the colony name "Pennsylvania" is found in a different form. This is the continuation of an anti-counterfeiting measure used by Franklin and Hall. Usually numbered in red ink and at least one of the three signatures in red. Denominations issued were: 4s, 6s, 14s and 16s.
  - Four Shillings2242 2242, 281; Signers: Ezekiel Edwards, Charles Wharton, Richard Vaux (in red).; Size: not available.
    Numbering and first two signatures in black ink, third signature in red ink. The top (or left) column on the front reads: "Light House" followed by "iv Shill." and the bottom (or right) column reads: "Piers and Buoys" followed by "iv Sh." The front also contains the Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice." Colony name appears as "Pensilvania ". No image of the back is available. The back of this denomination, which is inverted, displays a cast cut of a lighthouse with the denomination of the bill incised in roman numerals. The paper contains mica flakes.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 20, 1996, lot 550.
  - Sixteen Shillings828 828, 282; Signers: Samuel Coates, Charles Wharton (in red ink), William Wishart.; Size: 86 x 70mm (front border design: 85 x 68.5mm; back border design: 81 x 65mm).
    Numbered in black ink. Second signature in reddish-brown ink; others in black ink. The left column on the front reads downward: "Lighthouse" followed by a small xvi and the right column reads upward: "Piers & Buoys." followed by 16. The front also contains the Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice." The back, which is inverted, displays a cast cut of a lighthouse with the denomination of the bill incised in roman numerals (see lower left corner of the picture). Colony name appears as "Pennsylvania ". The paper contains mica flakes.
    6 o'clock
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 lot 440. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Pennsylvania Currency April 10, 1759Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaPennsylvaniaApril 10, 1775, PA 04/10/75; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission of ฃ25,000 in bills of credit for the construction of jails. The front of the bills is similar to the Franklin and Hall issue of April 25, 1759 with three border cuts and the Penn arms. This issue is printed in red and black by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia. The back contains an engraving of the Walnut Street Workhouse (jail) in Philadelphia and thus the issue is called the "Workhouse issue". The text on the back is upside down. The ฃ5 note comes in plates A and B while the 50s note come in plates C and D. Usually one of the three signers used red ink. Denominations issued were: 50s and ฃ5.
  PA 04.10.75
  - Fifty Shillings1137 1137, 283; Signers: Job Bacon, Lindsay Coats (in light red), Edward Roberts.; Size: 91 x 74mm (front border design: 85 x 71mm; back border design: 85 x 71mm).
    Numbered with first and third signatures in black ink. Second signature in red. Printed in red and black. The front contains the Penn family arms in red with the motto "Mercy Justice." The colony name is correctly spelled as "Pennsylvania" on this plate. The back, displays an engraving of the Walnut Street Workhouse or jail in Philadelphia. Also, the text above and below the workhouse were printed upside down. The paper contains mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 552. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Pennsylvania Currency July 20, 1775Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaPennsylvaniaJuly 20, 1775, PA 07/20/75; David Hall and William Sellers; James Smithers
  An emission of ฃ35,000 in bills of credit. Permission for this and subsequent issues were denied by the royal governor but the bills were issued pursuant to several legislative resolves, hence the bills from these issues are known as "resolve money." Interestingly, the Penn arms, which had been on all bills except the 1764 issue, was replaced by the British arms. Four border cuts on the front, one of which (on the 40s note) is signed by the designer of the cuts, James Smithers. Smithers, who later became a Tory sympathizer, also cut the dies for the Pitt Token. The backs feature nature prints. Bills from this emission were printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia on paper containing mica flakes and blue threads. Each denomination comes in plates A and B with a different spelling of the colony name "Pennsylvania" on each plate. This is the continuation of an anti-counterfeiting measure used by Franklin and Hall. Usually numbered in red ink and at least one of the three signatures in red. Denominations issued were: 10s, 20s, 30s and 40s.
  - Twenty Shillings3155 3155, 284; Signers: Thomas Pryor, Godfrey Twells (in red ink), Isaac Howell.; Size: 88 x 72mm (front border design: 86 x 68mm; back border design: 84 x 67mm).
    Numbered in red ink; second signature in red ink, rest in black ink. British Arms with G R for Georgius Rex appear on left. Below the denomination is keyed to four crowns. The two columns of the front are transposed in plate B. Colony name appears as "PENNSYLVANIA". Nature print on the back shows three fern branches. The paper contains mica flakes and blue threads.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 lot 443. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Twenty Shillings5912 5912, 285; Signers: Lambert Cadwalader, Samuel C. Morris, John Benezet.; Size: 90 x 72mm (front border design: 85 x 69mm; back border design: 84 x 67mm).
    Numbered and signed in brown ink. British Arms with G R for georgius Rex appears on left. below the denomination is keyed to four crowns. Colony name appears as "PENNSILVANIA". Nature print on the back contains three fern branches. The paper contains mica flakes and blue threads.
  - Ten Shillings5768 5768, 528; Signers: Thomas Pryor, Godfrey Twells, Isaac Howell.
    Number, first and last signature are in brown, the second signature is in red.
    EANA mail bid auction 12/1/07 lot 2095. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Pennsylvania Currency October 25, 1775Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaPennsylvaniaOctober 25, 1775, PA 10/25/75; David Hall and William Sellers; James Smithers
  An emission of ฃ22,000 in bills of credit as "resolve money" issued pursuant to the resolve of September 30, 1775 (see previous emission). The Penn arms were restored on the front of these bills. The 3d-9d are smaller in size, have plates A-C and have typeset backs. All have four front border cuts. The top border of the 1s note has an 'S' for the metalsmith James Smithers, who made the border cuts. The 'S' is quite small and is found just to the right of and below the cross stroke of the 'G' in the word "SHILLING." On our example it is very near the closely trimmed right border. Notes of 1s and up have nature prints on the back (except the 2s6d which has a chevron design of the back). Bills from this emission were printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia on paper containing mica flakes and blue threads. In each denomination the spelling of the colony name "Pennsylvania" is found in a different form. This is the continuation of an anti-counterfeiting measure used by Franklin and Hall. Usually numbered in red ink with at least one of the three signatures in red. Denominations issued were: 3d, 4d, 6d, 9d, 1s, 18d, 2s, 2s6d, 5s, 10s, 15s and 20s.
  - Nine Pence3996 3996, 286; Signer: Isaac Howell (in red).; Size: not available.
    Numbered and signed in red ink. The Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" appears in the left center of the front. The colony name appears as "Pensilvania". No image is available of the back. The paper contains mica flakes and blue threads.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 20, 1996, lot 554.
  - Eighteen Pence8012 8012, 288; Signers: Philip Kinsey, Charles Jervis, Thomas Shoemaker.; Size: not available.
    Numbered and signed in black ink. The Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" appears in right center of the front. The colony name appears as "Pennsilvania". No image is available of the nature print on the back which consists of a twig with five leaves. The paper contains mica flakes and blue threads.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 20, 1996, lot 555.
  - One Shilling19716 19716, 287; Signers: Thomas Tilbury, Isaac Howell (in red ink), Richard Humphreys.; Size: 89 x 70mm (front border design: 85 x 69mm; back border design: 86 x 63mm).
    Numbered in red ink; second signature in red ink, the other two are in black ink. The top border of the front has an 'S' for the metalsmith James Smithers, who made the border cuts (the 'S' is quite small and is found just to the right of and below the cross stroke of the 'G' in the word "SHILLING"). The Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" appears in left center of front. The colony name appears as "Pensylvania". Nature print on the back consisting of a twig with three leaves, there appears to be a signature below. The paper contains mica flakes and blue threads.
    EANA mail bid auction 12/2/95 lot 513. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Two Shillings10565 10565, 289; Signers: Jonathan Wardner, John Knowles, Abel Evans.
    Numbered and signed in black ink. The Penn family arms with the motto "Mercy Justice" appears in right center of the front. The colony name appears as "Pensylvania". The paper contains mica flakes and blue threads.